# **Alan Pearl**

■ US Citizen ■ alannpearl@outlook.com • AlanPearl • alannpearl • https://alanpearl.github.io

#### **Personal Statement**

Postdoctoral researcher in Astrophysics, seeking to apply my wide skillset as a machine learning engineer. I have over 8 years of experience in scientific software development, machine learning, algorithm derivation and implementation, big data analysis, relational database queries, Bayesian inference, and data visualization. I am the lead developer of many open-source software projects, e.g.  $\Omega$  diffopt,  $\Omega$  diffmahnet,  $\Omega$  galtab,  $\Omega$  JaxTabCorr, and  $\Omega$  mocksurvey.

# **Experience**

#### **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Sep 2023 - Present

Argonne National Laboratory, Lemont, IL

- Developed generative models of galaxy populations using neural networks, allowing my team to perform cosmological inference without requiring a million-CPU-hour simulation per evaluation
- Parallelized parameter optimization on distributed GPU clusters, utilizing our high-performance computing resources, enabling nearly limitless scalability of our models and up to 100x faster training times

#### **Graduate Student Researcher / Teaching Assistant**

Sep 2017 - Aug 2023

University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA

- Generated galaxy data catalogs through machine learning and developed new spatial clustering statistics that produced some of the most significant evidence of galaxy assembly bias to date
- Clear communication of complex concepts through teaching classes and advising undergraduate research

#### Education

University of Pittsburgh – Pittsburgh, PA	2017 - 2023
Ph.D. Physics - Thesis: Illuminating and Tabulating the Galaxy-Halo Connection	<i>Summer 2023</i>
M.S. Physics, GPA: 3.89	Dec 2018
Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute – Troy, NY	2013 - 2017
B.S. Physics, magna cum laude, GPA: 3.75	May 2017

#### **Technical Skills**

**Primary Language:** Python (over 8 years of scientific software development)

**Python Packages:** NumPy, Jax, Pandas, mpi4py, Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, SpaCy, LangChain

Secondary Languages: C++, C#, Cython, MATLAB, HTML, SQL, Mathematica, IDL

Operating Systems: Windows (with WSL), Linux (Ubuntu), AWS Certification: Amazon SageMaker

Other tools: Slurm, Git, GitHub CI, VS Code, Docker, DVC, debuggers (gdb, pdb)

## **First-Author and Advisee Publications**

<b>Dec 2024</b>	Pearl, Alan N.; Beltz-Mohrmann, Gillian D.; Hearin, Andrew P. 2024, JOSS, 9 (104), 7522.
Mar 2024	Pearl, Alan N.; Zentner, Andrew R.; Newman, Jeffrey A.; et al. 2024, ApJ, 963, 116
Jan 2024	Steel, Cecilia; Pearl, Alan N.; Kaushal, Yasha; Bezanson, Rachel 2024, RNAAS, 8, 16
Feb 2022	Pearl, Alan N.; Bezanson, Rachel; Zentner, Andrew R.; et al. 2022, ApJ, 925, 180P
Oct 2017	Pearl, Alan N.; Newberg, Heidi Jo; Carlin, Jeffrey L.; Smith, R. Fiona 2017, ApJ 847, 123P

## **Professional Reference**

Andrew Hearin ■ ahearin@anl.gov – current supervisor at Argonne National Laboratory